{"tossups": [{"question": "This city was blockaded after its leader hit Pierre Deval with a fly whisk. Viscount Exmouth bombarded this city after its leader refused to abolish Christian slavery; that bombing of this city allowed Stephen Decatur to end its impressment of American sailors. Omar Agha, a leader of this city, clashed with Decatur\u2019s forces during the Second Barbary War. For the point, name this city, historically ruled by a dey, that is now the capital of a North African country.", "answer": "<b> Algiers</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One side in this war accomplished its first ever naval victory in the Battle of Gangut, while the final, decisive naval battle in this war was the Battle of Grengam. The Greater Wrath and this war were ended by the Treaty of Nystad. Despite an early victory at Narva, a European empire faded after Carl Gustav Rehnskiold was crushed at Poltava. For the point, name this 18th century war between Peter the Great of Russia and Charles XII of Sweden.", "answer": "<b> Great Northern</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s Parian district is often regarded as the world\u2019s first Chinatown. This city was claimed for Spain by the Basque explorers Legazpi and Urdaneta, and this city named a type of ship that participated in transoceanic trade primarily with Acapulco. This city\u2019s Malacanang Palace was built on the Pasig River. A very large type of galleon was named for, for the point, what center of Spain\u2019s \u201cChina trade,\u201dthe largest city in the modern-day Philippines?", "answer": "<b> Manila</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Explorer Gertrude Bell persuaded the British government to support this dynasty during and after World War I after being captured by their rivals, the Rashids. This dynasty employed religious militia called the Ikhwan, or brothers, and this dynasty were early converts to the teachings of Abd al-Wahhab. This dynasty conquered Hejaz to gain custody of Islam\u2019s two holiest places. For the point, name this dynasty whose King Salman currently rules a namesake kingdom in the largest country on the Arabian Peninsula.", "answer": "House of<b> Sa\u2019ud</b> (accept<b> Saudi</b>s)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This composer\u2019s 8th string quartet begins with a motif symbolizing his own name. After this composer received a government denunciation, he described his next symphony as a \u201cresponse to just criticism.\u201dAnother of this composer\u2019s works includes a repeating ostinato called the \u201cInvasion Theme\u201d and was named for a city \u201cthat Stalin destroyed and Hitler merely finished off.\u201d For the point, name this Soviet composer of<em> Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District</em> and the<em> Leningrad</em> symphony.", "answer": "Dmitri<b> Shostakovich</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Along with perjury, this was the crime that Whittaker Chambers and Alger Hiss were accused of in the 1950s. In 1953, a Jewish couple was controversially executed for this crime. The Rosenbergs were executed for, for the point, what crime in which they passed state secrets to the Soviet Union?", "answer": "<b> espionage</b> (accept equivalent answers, like<b> spy</b>ing)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s father, Solomon Stoddard, supported the Half-Way Covenant. This New Light minister wrote a \u201cNarrative\u201d on the religious revival in Northampton, Massachusetts, and proclaimed it was the\u201cmere and arbitrary grace\u201d of God to grant people holiness. This grandfather of Aaron Burr gave his most famous address in 1741 in Enfield, Connecticut, where he noted that the \u201cmere pleasure of God\u201dkept wicked men out of Hell. For the point, name this Puritan preacher who wrote<em> Sinners in the Hands</em> <em>of an Angry God</em>.", "answer": "Jonathan<b> Edwards</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this event, Armand du Paty de Clam faked a hand injury to obtain a writing sample from a suspect. Georges Picquart uncovered that a memorandum in this event was actually written by Ferdinand Esterhazy. This event\u2019s main subject was sent to Devil\u2019s Island after being convicted of passing military secrets to the Germans in 1894. Emile Zola\u2019s letter \u201cJ\u2019Accuse\u201d concerned, for the point, what affair in which a Jewish French military officer was convicted of espionage?", "answer": "<b> Dreyfus</b> Affair (accept answers related to the<b> trial</b> or<b> imprisonment</b> of Alfred<b> Dreyfus</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A Prime Minister of Britain was told to \u201chit [this man] hard, hit him soon, and hit him by yourself,\u201dwhich led to Operation Kadesh. This man\u2019s pan-Arabic stance led to the United Arabic Republic with Syria. Anthony Eden resigned during a crisis that began when this leader seized the Suez Canal. This man replaced the head of the Free Officers Movement, Mohammed Naguib, in a 1954 coup. Anwar Sadat succeeded, for the point, what Egyptian ruler who built the Aswan High Dam and became President in 1956?", "answer": "Abdel Gamel<b> Nasser</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This thinker theorized about the origins of religion in his book<em> The Future of an Illusion</em>. In another work, this thinker theorized the \u201cdeath drive\u201d in an attempt to accomplish the title task of going<em> Beyond</em> <em>the Pleasure Principle</em>. This thinker, who developed a five-stage theory of psychosexual development, postulated the Oedipus Complex and wrote<em> The Interpretation of Dreams</em>. For the point, name this Austrian thinker, the founder of psychoanalysis.", "answer": "Sigmund<b> Freud</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "During a coup attempt against this man, Lu Buwei disguised Lao Ai as a eunuch in an attempt to win influence with the dowager queen. Jing Ke attempted to assassinate this man by hiding a dagger in a map after this man attacked the state of Yan. After defeating the kingdoms of Wei, Chu, and Zhao to take power, this man began construction on the Great Wall and buried dissenting Confucians alive. The Warring States Period ended with the rise of, for the point, what first emperor of China?", "answer": "Qin<b> Shi Huang</b>di (accept<b> Ying</b> Zheng; accept<b> Zhao</b> Zheng; accept<b> King Zheng</b> of Qin)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A personal vendetta against this man led to the veto of the Maysville Road. This politician proposed simultaneous statehood for Missouri and Maine as part of an 1820 agreement. This man supposedly benefited from the Corrupt Bargain that allowed him to become John Quincy Adams\u2019 Secretary of State. For the point, name this Kentucky politician, labeled the \u201cGreat Compromiser.\u201d", "answer": "Henry<b> Clay</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this campaign, a futile bayonet charge was led by Alexander Godfrey. Sir Frederick Stopford was dismissed after failing to attack after landing at Sulva Bay in this campaign. General Ian Hamilton persuaded forces to carry out the Battle of Lone Pine to draw attention away from this campaign\u2019s August Offensive. Otto Liman von Sanders opposed ANZAC forces during this campaign, in which Mustafa Kemal rose to military prominence by commanding Turkish troops. Winston Churchill was disgraced by the outcome of, for the point, what failed British campaign against the Ottoman Empire in World War I?", "answer": "<b> Gallipoli</b> Campaign (or the<b> Dardanelles</b> Campaign; accept similar descriptions, like the Battle of<b> Gallipoli</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "According to eyewitness accounts, this group\u2019s medics frequently used Coca-Cola to treat dysentery. This group purged its country\u2019s Cham Muslim population and harshly discriminated against \u201cNew People\u201d from its country\u2019s cities. This party overthrew the dictatorship of Lon Nol with the assistance of Prince Sihanouk, and was led by the \u201cCommittee\u201d, headed by a man formerly known as Saloth Sar. For the point, name this communist party led by Pol Pot in Cambodia.", "answer": "<b> Khmer Rouge</b> (prompt on descriptive answers of the communist party of Cambodia before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This battle was triggered by Catesby ap Roger Jones\u2019 attempted attack on the USS<em> Minnesota</em>. One vessel that participated in this battle was originally designed at the Gosport Naval Yard under the orders of Stephen Mallory; that warship had its components built at the Tredegar Works, faced off against another similar ship led by John Worden, and was later abandoned after failing to break the Union\u2019s blockade of Norfolk. For the point, name this 1862 Civil War battle that saw the clash of two ironclads.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Hampton Roads</b> (accept<b> Battle of the Ironclads</b> before \u201cIronclads\u201d is read; accept Battle of the USS<b> Monitor</b> and CSS<b> Merrimack</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An executive of this company compared his company\u2019s activities to the \u201cdelivery of our food supply.\u201dThe Sarbanes-Oxley Act was passed in response to this company\u2019s use of \u201cmark-to-market\u201d accounting under CFO Jeffrey Skilling, which helped cause the closure of the accounting firm Arthur Andersen. Kenneth Lay was indicted in Houston for unfair business practices as CEO of, for the point, what energy company whose accounting fraud led to its massive 2001 bankruptcy?", "answer": "<b> Enron</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s most influential leader was killed at the Battle of Mantinea [man-ti-nay-uh]. An elite force from this city-state was wiped out at the Battle of Chaeronea [care-oh-nay-uh] by the forces of Philip of Macedon. This city\u2019s general Epaminondas placed his strongest hoplites on his left flank to win the Battle of Leuctra [look-tra] over Sparta. The Sacred Band fought for, for the point, what central Greek city-state that dominated the region of Boeotia [bi-OH-shuh] and rivaled post-Golden Age Athens.", "answer": "<b> Thebes</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In the 14th century, Wang Dayuan wrote an early account of this city, where Fort Canning was built in 1861. When this city fell to Japan in 1942, Winston Churchill called it the \u201cworst disaster\u201d in British military history. Stamford Raffles built a British trading port in this city, which was ruled by the Sultan of Johor. The People\u2019s Action Party won the first election in this country, which saw growth under Lee Kuan Yew. For the point, name this Southeast Asian island city-state that was expelled from Malaysia in 1965.", "answer": "<b> Singapore</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A plan to increase this ruler\u2019s power was called \u201cThorough\u201d by advisor Thomas Wentworth, the first Earl of Strafford. This ruler was forced to sign the embarrassing Treaty of Ripon with the Covenanters, and his attempts to call \u201cship money\u201d taxes ended in fiasco. The Long Parliament was first called by this king, and it was purged by his successor, Oliver Cromwell. For the point, name this English King who succeeded James I and was executed following his loss in the English Civil War.", "answer": "<b> Charles I</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Argersinger v. Hamlin extended the decision from this case, whose winning side was represented by future disgraced Supreme Court justice Abe Fortas. This court case extended<em> Powell v. Alabama</em> while overturning<em> Betts v. Brady</em>. The defendant in this case was arrested after allegedly breaking into a Florida pool hall. For the point, name this court case that guaranteed the right to an attorney in criminal trials, even if the defendant could not afford one.", "answer": "<b> Gideon</b> v. Wainwright", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Annually on this day of the week, Eastern Orthodox churches change their vestamental colors from red or purple to black. Along with Wednesday, Eastern Orthodox Christians traditionally abstain from animal products on this day of the week, and Roman Catholics originally abstained from meat on this day. On this day of the week, Muslims gather for the Jumu\u2019ah prayer service. For the point, give this day of the week on which Jesus\u2019s crucifixion is commemorated, celebrated by Christians as \u201cGood.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Friday</b> (accept Good<b> Friday</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "Both the Bonneville Dam and the Rocky Reach Dam on this river pioneered the use of juvenile fish bypass systems to help salmon migration. Lewis and Clark spent the winter of 1805 at Fort Clatsop on the shores of this river at the future site of Fort Astoria. Lake Franklin Delano Roosevelt was created on this river by the completion of the Grand Coulee Dam. The Snake River is a tributary of, for the point, what large river in the Pacific northwest?", "answer": "<b> Columbia</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The nobility in this country was known as<em> szlachta</em> [sh\u2019lock-ta], and many were murdered by peasants in the Galician slaughter. This country\u2019s last king, Stanislaw Poniatowski, helped write its Constitution of 3rd May before he was defeated by Catherine the Great. For the point, name this country that endured 3 partitions after the fall of its commonwealth with Lithuania.", "answer": "<b> Poland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man sharply criticized the Teamsters Union and Jimmy Hoffa in a book that drew on his work as chief counsel on the McClellan Committee,<em> The Enemy Within</em>.<em> Thirteen Days</em> was a posthumously-published work by this man detailing his role in the Cuban Missile Crisis. This man spoke on the \u201cmindless menace of violence\u201d in Cleveland a day after giving an impromptu speech after the death of Martin Luther King. For the point, name this politician who was a candidate for the Democratic presidential nomination when he was assassinated by Sirhan Sirhan in 1968, five years after the death of his brother.", "answer": "<b> R</b>obert Fitzgerald<b> Kennedy</b> (or<b> RFK</b>; prompt on Kennedy)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Andrew Beckett, a lawyer who suffers from this disease, is played by Tom Hanks in the 1993 film <em>Philadelphia</em>. Ron Woodroof\u2019s illegal smuggling of drugs to fight this disease are the subject of a 2013 film that won Matthew McConaughey an Oscar,<em> Dallas Buyers Club</em>. In 2003, HBO aired a miniseries version of Tony Kushner\u2019s play about this disease,<em> Angels in America</em>. For the point, name this disease whose 1980s epidemic also provides the setting for Jonathan Larsen\u2019s<em> Rent</em>.", "answer": "<b> HIV</b>/<b>AIDS</b> (accept either or both; accept<b> Human Immunodeficiency Virus</b> and/or <b>Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</b>; accept<b> Kaposi\u2019s sarcoma</b>) (31) This man ordered the execution of folk hero \u201cBreaker\u201d Morant, an Australian soldier accused of shooting civilians. This man, who was killed on the<em> Hampshire</em> when his ship struck a mine in the North Sea, expanded the usage of concentration camps after he succeeded Lord Roberts as commander in the Boer War. This man rose to fame after the Battle of Omdurman, where he secured the British reconquest of the Sudan. For the point, name this Secretary of State for War who \u201cwants you,\u201d according to a famous World War I recruitment poster. ANSWER: Horatio Herbert<b> Kitchener</b>, 1st Earl Kitchener (accept Lord<b> Kitchener</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Sam Anderson\u2019s<em> Boom Town</em> observes that this man\u2019s failed $1,000 wager on the Buffalo Bills\u2019 third of four straight Super Bowl losses came just days before he abandoned his home in Buffalo and drove to Waco to show support for the besieged Branch Davidians. Three days after this man was jailed for driving without a license plate and having an illegal concealed gun, he was charged with committing an attack on the Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building that killed 168 people in 1995. For the point, name this domestic terrorist who committed the Oklahoma City bombing.", "answer": "Timothy<b> McVeigh</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Leading up to this event, Bruce MacKenzie was instrumental in allowing intelligence gathering. This event was preceded by a hijacking that Waddie Hadad ordered the PFLP-EO to carry out. Dora Bloch was murdered and her body was left in a field in the aftermath of this event, in which Yonatan Netanyahu was killed in action. Idi Amin condemned this action, which took place in his country\u2019s largest airport. For the point, name this Israeli operation that rescued 100 hostages in 1976.", "answer": "Operation<b> Entebbe</b> (accept descriptions of the<b> Entebbe</b> Raid; accept<b> Operation Thunderbolt</b> and<b> Operation Jonathan</b> before \u201cYonatan\u201d is read; prompt on descriptions that don\u2019t use the word \u201cEntebbe\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Portugal was eventually added to this ruler\u2019s domain after King Sebastian vanished in North Africa and this man won the Battle of Alcantara. This man supposedly laughed for the first time after hearing of the St. Bartholomew\u2019s Day Massacre in France. His attempts to attack England were eventually thwarted at the Battle of Gravelines [grahv-uh-leen], where fire ships were used against his fleet. Queen Elizabeth gave the Tilbury speech to rally support against the forces of, for the point, what king who sent out the Spanish Armada?", "answer": "<b> Philip II</b> of Spain (accept<b> Philip I of Portugal</b>, but do not accept or prompt on \u201cPhilip I\u201dalone; prompt on Philip alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Ruth Bader Ginsburg compared discarding a section of this law to \u201cthrowing away your umbrella in a rainstorm because you are not getting wet.\u201d A year after this law was passed, this law\u2019s formula was upheld by<em> South Carolina v. Katzenbach</em>; in 2013, that formula for preclearance requirements was struck down by<em> Shelby County v. Holder</em> as unconstitutional. Literacy tests and other methods of disenfranchisement were banned by, for the point, what 1965 civil rights law that banned racial discrimination at the polls?", "answer": "<b> Voting Rights</b> Act of 1965 (accept<b> VRA</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Biswanath Sardar was hung for leading a revolt over growing this cash crop, which was incentivized with large loans called \u201cdadon.\u201d Benjamin Franklin sailed on the<em> U.S.S. Reprisal</em> with 35 barrels of this commodity to negotiate with France. After rice, this commodity became the second largest cash crop grown in South Carolina, following its popularization by Eliza Pinckney. This plant was farmed as an alternative to Murex snails to create Tyrian Purple. For the point, name this crop of the colonial American South that can be processed into a deep blue dye.", "answer": "<b> Indigo</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Battle of Karameh failed to completely eliminate this political party, thanks to the tactics of its<em> fedayeen</em> guerillas. This party\u2019s attempts to overthrow the Hashemite monarchy under Hussein II led to its expulsion from Jordan. The 1972 Munich Massacre was carried out by a splinter cell of this party, Black September. Mahmoud Abbas currently chairs this party, which was founded by Yasser Arafat. For the point, name this Palestinian political party that is opposed to Hamas.", "answer": "<b> Fatah</b> (prompt on Palestinian National Liberation Movement)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s findings confirmed ones Abel Niepce de Saint Victor had made thirty years prior. This man was unable to expose his photographic plates to sun on an overcast day, allowing him to determine the link between phosphorescence and X-rays. This man shared the 1903 Nobel Prize with his doctoral student, Marie Curie, who aided him on experiments with uranium. For the point, name this French scientist, the namesake of the SI unit for radioactivity.", "answer": "Henri<b> Becquerel</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "This man took advantage of the death of Rabbel Il Soter to peacefully annex Nabataea. In another war, this man captured the fortress of Sarmizegetusa Regia and had to twice destroy its walls after they were rebuilt; that war featured the construction of a namesake bridge across the Danube built by this man\u2019s architect, Apollodorus of Damascus. Decebalus was defeated in the Dacian War by, for the point, what second of the Five Good Emperors who grew the Roman Empire to its greatest size and who is commemorated by a namesake Roman column?", "answer": "<b> Trajan</b> (or<b> Caesar Nerva Traianus Germanicus</b> or<b> Caesar Divi Nervae Filius Nerva Traianus Optimus Augustus</b>, but do not prompt on partial answers thereof)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "One leader with this surname promised that his country would \u201ceat grass\u201d in order to get a nuclear weapon; that leader with this surname was hanged by the government of Zia ul-Haq. The PPP Party was led for most of its existence by politicians with this surname, one of whom was assassinated in 2007 in Rawalpindi and was her country\u2019s first female Prime Minister. For the point, give this surname of Zulfikar Ali and Benazir, two Prime Ministers of Pakistan.", "answer": "<b> Bhutto</b> (accept Zulfikar Ali<b> Bhutto</b> and/or Benazir<b> Bhutto</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This politician had a long-term affair with Marietta Tree, who was with him when he died in 1965. This man defeated Dwight Green in a 1948 statewide election, partially due to Green\u2019s poor handling of the Centralia mine disaster. Richard Nixon accused this politician of holding a Ph.D. from Dean Acheson\u2019s\u201ccowardly College of Communist Containment.\u201d Bill Gallagher won a Pulitzer for a picture depicting this man with a hole in his shoe while on the campaign trail in 1952. For the point, name this politician from Illinois who lost two presidential elections to Dwight Eisenhower.", "answer": "Adlai E.<b> Stevenson</b> II", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Prisoner of war camps for people captured during this campaign served as the recruiting grounds for the Trawniki men. The targets of this campaign were to be starved out by the strategies of the Hunger Plan. The Great Patriotic War began after this event, in which Army Group South planned on taking control of the oil reserves of the Caucasus. Afraid of Napoleon\u2019s failure, the overseer of this 1941 campaign focused on destroying the Red Army rather than taking Moscow. For the point, name this Nazi invasion of Russia.", "answer": "Operation<b> Barbarossa</b> (prompt on descriptions of the Nazi invasion of Russia before the end)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s mother-in-law Alexandra tried to plot against him by appealing to Cleopatra to make Aristobulus III high priest, forcing this man to execute Aristobulus III. In the Gospel of Matthew, this man orders the death of every child less than two in Bethlehem. This man built the port of Caesarea Maritima and the fortress of Masada and he helped rebuild the Second Temple. As a Roman client king, this man took power following the fall of the Hasmonean Dynasty of Judea. For the point, name this Great king of Judea.", "answer": "<b> Herod</b> the Great", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Vladimir Horowitz refused to play a challenging piece by this composer nicknamed \u201cWaterfall.\u201d This composer allegedly said, \u201cAll this has caused me much pain. Who could have foreseen it!\u201d in response to a November 1831 uprising against the Russians in this composer\u2019s home country. That uprising inspired a piece that was published with this composer\u2019s \u201cBlack Key\u201d etude in a collection dedicated to Franz Liszt. The \u201cRevolutionary\u201d Etude was composed by, for the point, what Polish pianist?", "answer": "Fr\u00b4ed\u00b4eric Fran\u00b8cois<b> Chopin</b> (accept Fryderyk Franciszek<b> Chopin</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "With Aragon, a king with this name signed the Treaty of Almirzra to define conquests in Andalusia. Gonzalo de C\u00b4ordoba served a king of this name, capturing Naples and Granada. Boabdil of the Nasrid Dynasty was defeated by forces under a king of this name and his wife. This man was the regent for Joanna the Mad before Charles V took power. A king of this name sponsored Christopher Columbus\u2019s expedition to the New World. For the point, a king of Aragon with what name married Isabella of Castille to unite Spain?", "answer": "<b> Ferdinand</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Suetonius made note of one of these works in Rome that noted \u201cA calculation new. Nero his mother slew.\u201d Anoter work of this type notes \u201cI love her whose number is 545\u201d and was discovered in the ruins at Pompeii. In Egypt, these artworks were often scrawled in red paint by construction gangs at sites such as the Great Pyramid. A modern creator of this type of artwork drew nine images on the West Bank wall. For the point, name this art form produced by Banksy, who creates often political statements using spray paint.", "answer": "<b> graffiti</b> (or<b> graffito</b>; prompt on descriptions of vandalism)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The Battle of Uji took place near this city during the Genpei War, which ended a period in which this city was the capital. For the point, name this city that was Japan\u2019s capital during the Heian Period.", "answer": "<b> Kyoto</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "There are five permanent members of the Security Council within, for the point, what international peacekeeping organization?", "answer": "<b> U</b>nited<b> N</b>ations", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "William Livingston opposed funding this institution in his opposition to the Anglican faction, although that didn\u2019t stop Samuel Johnson from founding this school. The Philolexian Society was founded at this school that, in 1784, named George Clinton as its chancellor. Myles Cooper was defended from a mob at this location due to a speech by then-student Alexander Hamilton. King\u2019s College evolved into, for the point, what New York university that is now part of the Ivy League?", "answer": "<b> Columbia</b> University (accept Anglican<b> King\u2019s</b> College before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader established a new capital that absorbed the city of Avaris and may have been used as a supply depot for his Syrian campaigns. A weakening of this leader\u2019s relations with the Canaan princes and accusations that he harbored Mursili III pulled this man into a conflict with his northern rivals. This man commissioned the temples of Abu Simbel and dedicated them to his wife Nefertari. Muwatalli II was defeated by this man in a battle that resulted in the world\u2019s first recorded peace treaty. For the point, name this Egyptian Pharaoh who won the Battle of Kadesh.", "answer": "<b> Ramesses II</b> (accept<b> Ramesses the Great</b>; prompt on Ramesses; prompt on Ozymandias)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In Matthew chapter 20, a landowner who had distributed these objects asks \u201care you envious because I am generous?\u201d and questions \u201cDon\u2019t I have the right to do what I want with my own money?\u201d In that story, a day laborer complains that another received this object for only an hour\u2019s work. This coin was compared by Jesus to the Kingdom of Heaven and paid out in the Parable of the Workers in the Vineyard. For the point, name this Roman silver coin from whose name the Spanish word for money derives.", "answer": "<b> denarius</b> (or<b> denarii</b>; prompt on (silver) coin before mentioned)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "After a Senator was involved in one of these events, Walter Mondale earned the distinction of losing a political race in every US state; Mondale had replaced the late Paul Wellstone as a candidate. Tip O\u2019Neill replaced Hale Boggs as House Majority Leader after Boggs was involved in one of these events. Ted Stevens, who survived one of these events in 1978, died in one shortly after he was cleared from his federal corruption charge. For the point, name this type of tragedy that was intentionally caused by terrorists on 9/11.", "answer": "<b> plane crash</b>es", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Doubts of Yue Fei\u2019s loyalty to this dynasty led to his execution. This dynasty attempted to recover the Sixteen Prefectures, and used paddle-wheel ships. In the Jingkang incident, its capital Kaifeng was captured by the Jin dynasty, marking the boundary between its northern and southern periods. This dynasty was crushed at the Battle of Yamen and was the first to use paper money and gunpowder. For the point, name this Chinese dynasty that was defeated by the Mongols.", "answer": "<b> Song</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This event was made worse by inflammatory radio broadcasts by the RTLM, and it was precipitated by the shooting down of a plane carrying President Juv\u00b4enal Habyarimana. Kofi Annan refused to allow a U.N. peacekeeping force to intervene against this event\u2019s perpetrators, a group of radical Hutus who used machetes against the Tutsis. For the point, name this months-long event in which more than a million people were killed in Africa in 1994.", "answer": "<b> Rwanda</b>n<b> Genocide</b> (accept descriptive answers of a<b> genocide</b> of the<b> Tutsi</b>s/by the<b> Hutu</b>s before either is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This ruler built the first printing yard in his country, though the printers fled to Lithuania after an arson attack. Richard Chancellor established relations between this ruler and England by sailing through the White Sea to Archangel. To celebrate the Siege of Kazan, this ruler constructed St. Basil\u2019s Cathedral. This ruler was succeeded by the ineffectual Feodor after he murdered his son in a fit of rage. For the point, name this Russian monarch, the first to claim the title of Tsar.", "answer": "<b> Ivan IV</b> (or<b> Ivan the Terrible</b>; or<b> Ivan Grozny</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A secessionist province of this country gained the right to impose a form of sharia law in 2002. The Free South Moluccan Youth was a terror group from this country, where the Free Aceh [ah-chay] Movement operated until a 2004 natural disaster. For the point, name this Southeast Asian country that granted independence to East Timor in 2002 and was the land nearest to the epicenter of the 2004 Indian Ocean earthquake and tsunami.", "answer": "<b> Indonesia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This present-day body of water\u2019s fishing industry, based in towns such as Karateren, relies mostly on bream and carp and has increased sharply since 2005. This body of water is located in its country\u2019s Kyzylorda Region, and a former port town that partially shares its name with this body of water is now 20 kilometers from its shores. The 2005 installation of a dike on its south coast has allowed this lake to keep more water from the Syr Darya River, whose over-irrigation led to this lake\u2019s creation. For the point name this portion of a formerly large inland sea, a recently-formed lake located entirely in Kazakhstan.", "answer": "<b> North Aral</b> Sea (prompt on Aral Sea alone)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "One monarch with this name was the subject of a poem labeling him \u201cwarlike as a pard, sweet as a spikenard.\u201d Another monarch of this name was overthrown by an invasion coordinated by Roger Mortimer and his wife, Isabella of France; that monarch with this name may have had an affair with the courtier Piers Gaveston. Another monarch of this name was nicknamed \u201cHammer of the Scots\u201d for his defeat of William Wallace. For the point, give this royal name shared by a 20th century ruler who abdicated to marry Wallis Simpson and by a 13th century ruler nicknamed \u201cLongshanks.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Edward</b> (accept<b> Edward I</b>,<b> Edward II</b>,<b> Edward VIII</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A rhyming slogan coined in this country in 1672 described it as senseless, leaderless, and rudderless during its \u201cyear of disaster,\u201d which culminated in the lynching of the De Witt brothers. Balthasar Gerard assassinated a monarch from this country, where the Duke of Alva used brutal tactics in a failed attempt to crush a revolt during the Eighty Years\u2019 War that culminated in its independence. For the point, name this country that was led by Stadtholders like William the Silent.", "answer": "the<b> Netherlands</b> (accept<b> United Provinces</b>; accept the<b> Dutch</b> Republic)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s independence was secured by an Indian invasion after refugees flooded cities like Kolkata from this country. For the point, name this country that was known as East Pakistan before its independence and which now has its capital at Dhaka.", "answer": "<b> Bangladesh</b> (accept<b> East Pakistan</b> before mentioned; do not prompt on Pakistan alone)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This colonel may have committed a war crime when he ambushed a group of Canadians under Joseph Jumonville during peacetime. As a member of the Virginia Regiment, the first professional American force, this man led the Forbes expedition to capture Fort Duquesne [do-cane]. Upon that expedition\u2019s failure, this man was forced to build and then surrender Fort Necessity in 1754, helping start the French and Indian War. For the point, name this American general who later served as commander-in-chief of the Continental Army during the American Revolution.", "answer": "George<b> Washington</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}